Hi, welcome back to
Nagarjuna number three.
We've reached now Chapter 14.
And this is called PHRAD PA BRTAG PA
PHRAD PA BRTAG PA
You guys know BRTAG PA
because that's 'pariksha'.
Pariksha means
'an investigation', so
each of these chapters
is a separate investigation.
It's like Nagarjuna's the police
or a detective and he's
investigating different people,
different things in the universe,
and this one is called PHRAD PA BRTAG PA.
He's investigating can
something touch something else?
PHRAD PA, can something
make contact with something else?
We've been talking about it all along,
but here's a whole chapter dedicated to:
can something touch something else?
By the way, if it cannot
touch something else,
then that draws into
question causation itself.
If you put gas in a car, but
the engine can't touch the gas,
then what's making the car go?
Okay?
Here we go with the first verse.
We know that we have to watch out for
possible... this might be the other guy,
but I'm going to make it easy for you
and tell you the first verse here is us.
The first two verses is us.
So here we go.
BLTA BYA LTA BA LTA BA PO
[Sneezes]
Is there any contact between
my nose and the tissue paper?
[students Llughing]
,BLTA BYA LTA BA LTA BA PO,
,GSUM PO DE DAG GNYIS GNYIS DANG,
,THAMS CAD KYANG NI PHAN TSUN DU,
,PHRAD PAR 'GYUR PA YOD MA YIN,
So he's going to discuss
a kind of a difficult kind of touching.
When I look at Rebecca, right now,
I have... Rebecca is the BLTA BYA,
the 'lookee', the thing I'm looking at.
LTA BA means 'the looking'
and LTA BA PO is me, the 'looker'.
Those three. Do they ever make contact?
What kind of contact, Geshe-la?
Do these two, do these
two, or do these two
to make contact,
which means GNYIS GNYIS DANG,
do they make dual contact?
Or THAMS CAD KYANG NI PHAN TSUN DU
means do the three ever touch each other?
So we got some different
possibilities, right?
Geshe-la,'looker';
Rebecca being 'looked at';
and then the verb 'of looking' -
do those there ever touch each other?
And do any two touch each other?
Does Geshe-la touch the looking?
Or does the looking touch Rebecca?
Or does the... Geshe-la
touch Rebecca somehow?
Is there any touch going
on between those three,
any combination of touching?
,DE BZHIN 'DOD CHAGS CHAGS PA DANG,
,CHAGS PAR BYA BA
And then let's take it to
your negative emotions,
which is a big part of
Buddhist practice, right?
When you want something bad enough
to hurt somebody to get it,
then there's the 'wanter',
there's 'the wanting',
and there's 'the thing you want'.
Do they ever touch?
Or do any combination of
them touch each other?
So he starts out with something
innocuous, like looking,
and then he's going to take
it to negative emotions:
hating somebody or wanting something
bad enough to steal it.
CHAGS PAR BYA BA, and then he says...
By the way, you have
to read over the verse,
over the lines here, or you won't get it.
NYON MONGS PA, LHAG MA
Which means and then let's talk about
all the other mental afflictions.
We got desire covered here:
'desirer', 'desiree', and the 'desiring'.
And then he says... and then you have to
read across the lines,
NYON MONGS PA, LHAG MA
The rest of these,
DANG SKYE MCHED KYI LHAG MA
Then let's... By the way,
SKYE MCHED means in Abhidharma.
Here it means 'the senses'.
So we talked about seeing,
but what about hearing,
what about smelling, what about tasting,
what about feeling?
Does the feeler ever touch the...
Does the feeler ever touch
the object that they're feeling?
And does your jealousy ever touch
what you're jealous about?
So let's talk about all those things.
I have a picture here of a lady.
When you want money,
and then I keep saying,
enough to hurt someone to get it,
I say you cannot touch the money.
When you want money bad enough
that you will hurt someone else,
I say you cannot touch the money.
You never touch the money.
So that's a... you've
got to think about it.
Can you touch money if
you want to give it away?
Yes.
Maybe.
Can you touch money if
you want to steal it?
Never.
All right.
We're going to learn some
Sanskrit here right away.
'sansarga'
This is not Sansara.
It's Sansarga.
This means 'touching', making contact.
It has two parts, 'san-',
or 'sam-', and 'sarga'.
By itself, sam, when in combination with S
it changes to S-A-N.
The pronunciation
changes to san, sansarga.
So san- means 'together',
it comes from 'sam',
that changes the C-O, like
'committee' or 'convention',
coming together or meeting together,
sending together, committee.
So the 'com' is easy, the C-O-M is easy.
What's the 'sarga'?
It comes from √sṛj,
which is a Sanskrit root,
and that means 'to move together'
or 'to move towards each other'.
And to surge, we have that
verb in English, sansarga.
In Indo-European, which is also
a kind of an ancient Sanskrit, S drops out
and this √sṛj becomes √reg,
and it means 'to regulate'
or 'to reign over something'
or to... or the right way.
So it means 'straight',
'to move straight'.
By itself, surge means 'to move towards',
san- means 'the two things move together'
and they touch.
So that's sansarga.
Is it possible that things ever
surge towards each other?
Sansarga. Yes or no? Here we go.
All right, next verse.
,GZHAN DANG GZHAN DU PHRAD 'GYUR NA,
,GANG PHYIR BLTA BYA LA SOGS LA,
,GZHAN DE YOD PA MA YIN PA,
,DE PHYIR PHRAD PAR MI 'GYUR RO,
Now here's our comment on touching.
GZHAN DANG GZHAN DU PHRAD 'GYUR NA
If two things which are
different from each other
can touch each other,
GANG PHYIR BLTA BYA LA SOGS LA,
GZHAN DE YOD PA MA YIN PA
I'm asking you,
can your eye touch your seeing?
Can your eye, can the 'seer'
make contact with the 'seeing'?
If not, the seer cannot see.
If the seer cannot touch the seeing,
if the seer never makes
contact with the seeing,
then they must be smelling, for example.
So do they ever make contact?
Yes.
Does seer, the eye, ever touch the seeing?
They have to.
Does the seeing ever touch Rebecca?
It has too.
PHRAD 'GYUR NA
But if they touch, GZHAN DE YOD PA MA YIN
then they have to be separate,
and if they're separate, they don't exist.
Or there's no such thing as other,
that Geshe-la cannot be
different from Rebecca
if Geshe-la can see Rebecca.
They cannot be different.
DE PHYIR PHRAD PAR MI 'GYUR RO
Therefore, there is no sansarga.
What does that mean?
Things never touch each other.
Things never contact each other.
When I open my eyes,
it's not the opening my eyes
that makes me see Rebecca.
Something else has happened.
What's happening?
Seeds are opening in Geshe-la's mind
and Geshe-la sees Rebecca.
In the Mind-Only School,
she's never outside of my mind.
I'm just watching pictures in my own mind.
But in the higher
schools, she is out there,
she is a separate person,
but the reason I see
her as separate from me
is that seeds are opening in my mind
for me to see her as separate from me.
And it's not that my eye is seeing her.
It's not in my eye is making contact.
The theme of my next picture is
things that don't exist
cannot touch each other.
A self-existent eye could not
touch self-existent seeing
to reach a self-existent Rebecca.
It's not... you can't have contact,
you can't have a war between
these two rabbits with horns.
And this is the classic Buddhist example
of something that's impossible.
They call it a 'jackalope' in the West.
Jack-rabbit-antelope or something.
So try to imagine two
things that don't exist
touching each other,  and
you've got the right picture.
All right, next verse.
,BLTA BYA LA SOGS 'BA' ZHIG LA,
,GZHAN NYID MED PAR MA ZAD KYI,
Let's start with that, because
it's already difficult.
BLTA BYA LA SOGS
Now we had three elements in the act
of Geshe-la seeing Rebecca:
there was the 'see-ee', which is Rebecca;
there's the 'seer' which is Geshe-la;
and then there's the
'seeing' between them.
Now let's take them individually.
He says 'BA' ZHIG.
Let's just take Rebecca without the seeing
and without Geshe-la looking.
GZHAN NYID MED PAR MA ZAD KYI
She cannot be considered
separate because she's alone.
Got it? That's a little tricky.
Let's forget Geshe-la. Forget the looking.
Let's just talk about Rebecca.
Now, what kind of relationships
have we got there?
Well, zero, because
something has to be different
to have a relationship.
A person can't have relationship
with exactly the same person,
because there's only one.
So eliminate that one.
Nagarjuna says that one's easy.
Take one of the three elements of seeing -
seer, seeing, and seen -
and just treat one of them:
'BA' ZHIG, seen,
can it have a relationship?
No, we don't have to talk about that one.
Well let's talk ,GANG YANG
GANG DANG LHAN CIG TU,
Let's talk about two of them
sitting in the same room:
Geshe-la and Rebecca.
,GZHAN PA NYID DU MI 'THAD DO, well then
they couldn't be something else.
They can't be something else
if they're only one thing.
And they can't be something
else if they're not one thing.
That's Nagarjuna.
If they're not one thing,
they can't be something else
because to you something
else means out there,
from it's own side.
That's all.
You got to keep remembering that.
For some reason, I thought it was
really clever to have a cherry
that was itself
but something else at the same time.
[Laughing]
Look, it's hard to find
picture like that [laughs].
All right, nevermind.
Well, I'm not going to say a bad word.
All right.
You are witness, I do
have some self control.
Okay, next verse.
,GZHAN NI GZHAN LA BRTEN TE GZHAN,
,GZHAN MED PAR GZHAN GZHAN MI 'GYUR,
,GANG LA BRTEN TE GANG YIN PA,
,DE NI DE LAS GZHAN MI 'THAD,
This is very difficult, let's
go through line by line.
GZHAN NI GZHAN LA BRTEN TE GZHAN
Others are others relative to others.
That's okay.
And he uses the classical example
of a water vase and a bolt of cloth.
You could say a car and a refrigerator.
Let's use that.
When you say a car is
different from a refrigerator,
the difference is drawn by
observing both together.
A car can only be different
from a refrigerator
if you see the other thing that's there
before you decide it's different.
You've got to have two things there.
GZHAN MED PAR GZHAN GZHAN MI 'GYUR
If there was no car,
you couldn't call the
refrigerator different from... ?
There has to be something else there.
GANG LA BRTEN TE GANG YIN PA
Anything that is something
relative to something else,
DE NI DE LAS GZHAN MI 'THAD
Could never be other than it.
Nothing which is different from
something else by comparison
could be called something else,
self-existently.
Nothing which is something
else by comparison,
a refrigerator is different from a car,
but it cannot be called
different in and of itself.
Once you get into dependence,
even if you're not speaking
about dependence on mental seeds,
you're already messing with
the fact that something
could be self-existent.
Once you say something
depends on something else,
you've already almost left
the realm of self-existence.
The word 'dependent origination',
or occurring in reliance.
Once you get into comparison
or one thing depending on another,
it's difficult to start asserting that
they are both self-existent,
and they exist in and of themselves.
All right.
No one is tall where tall
and short are compared.
Okay.
So this is a little tricky.
Normally, you've got that picture?
Normally you would say the young girl
is short by comparison to
her mother or her sister,
I don't know who it is, her mom I guess.
Normally you would say
she's short compared to her mom.
Normally you would say that.
And Nagarjuna says if the mom is tall...
If you can only call the mom tall
by comparison to her
daughter, then she's not tall.
I'll say it again. If you
can only call the mom tall
by comparison to her short daughter,
then we can't really say the mom is tall.
Got it?
'Really say' means in and of herself,
meaning self-existently.
Is she tall?
I don't know.
Is she tall compared to her daughter?
Yes.
Then she's not tall.
If she's only tall with
reference to something else,
then she's not tall in herself.
Got it?
That's easy, right?
We understood one verse, all right.
[students Laughing]
Where are you going after that, Nagarjuna?
,GAL TE GZHAN NI GZHAN LAS GZHAN,
,DE TSE GZHAN MED PAR GZHAN 'GYUR,
,GZHAN MED PAR NI GZHAN 'GYUR PA,
,YOD MIN DE YI PHYIR NA MED,
GAL TE GZHAN NI GZHAN LAS GZHAN
if a car is self-existently
different from a refrigerator,
DE TSE GZHAN MED PAR GZHAN 'GYUR
in that case something which
is not different became different.
If a car is only a car
relative to a refrigerator,
then a car, which was
different, is not different.
GZHAN MED PAR NI GZHAN 'GYUR PA
GZHAN MED PAR here means
'that which doesn't have another'.
That which doesn't have another,
meaning the mom by herself.
The tall mom by herself.
GZHAN MED PAR NI GZHAN 'GYUR PA
If the mom were tall,
GZHAN MED PAR
without the girl around,
YOD MIN DE YI PHYIR NA MED
then she wouldn't be tall.
If the mom were tall by
comparison to the daughter,
she wouldn't be tall because
she's not tall by herself.
She's only tall by comparison.
All right.
A coffee cup is not different
from a pair of jeans.
I was trying to find a... I
was trying to get this lady,
I was trying to find a lady drinking,
somebody drinking coffee with jeans on.
Is the coffee cup the jeans?
No.
Is the coffee cup
different from the jeans?
- [Student] Only if the jeans are there.
- Yeah, only if the jeans are there,
which means it's not different by itself.
It's not really different,
because it's only different by comparison.
Is coffee different from jeans?
- [Student] Yes.
- Yeah.
Why?
Because when you look at the coffee cup
you see it doesn't look
like the jeans, right?
Then that difference is
dependent on something else,
and it's not part of the coffee cup.
Okay?
All right.
Somewhere it applies to
racism in there I think.
Next verse.
,GZHAN NYID GZHAN LA YOD MA YIN,
,GZHAN MA YIN LA'ANG YOD MA YIN,
,GZHAN NYID YOD PA MA YIN NA,
,GZHAN NAM DE NYID YOD MA YIN,
GZHAN NYID GZHAN LA YOD MA YIN
Being something other
is not part of anything which is other.
Being other is not part of being other.
Being other is not part
of something other.
GZHAN MA YIN LA'ANG YOD MA YIN
Neither is that other not an other.
GZHAN NYID YOD PA MA YIN NA
If there is no other,
which is general otherness -
otherness as a concept -
GZHAN NYID
is being treated as otherness.
If there's no such thing as otherness,
then there's no other, and other
in the sense of being one
and the same by comparison.
If there is no otherness by itself,
then there can't be
otherness by comparison.
If there's no concept of otherness,
then you can't have
otherness by comparison,
because that's what the concept
of otherness applies to,
is otherness by comparison.
If otherness by comparison were real,
it wouldn't need to be
compared with something else.
If something's only something
by comparison with something else,
then it's not really that thing.
It's partly the other thing.
So therefore the idea of
otherness is questionable.
(thinking)
Got a picture here.
Are they other or are they the same?
Huh?
What? huh?
- [Student] Who's asking?
What's the picture of?
- It's a duck with a goose and a chicken.
Are they other or are they the same?
Compared to each other they're
other, but they're all fowls.
Is this a picture of same things
or is this a picture of different things?
Depends on what you compare it to.
Anyway, I thought it was a cute example.
All right, let's keep going here.
,DE NI DE DANG PHRAD PA MED,
,GZHAN DANG GZHAN YANG PHRAD MI 'GYUR
When you talk about two
things making contact,
is it that one thing
makes contact with itself?
Can Rebecca make contact with Rebecca?
No, cannot, right?
We're talking about Michael seeing,
act of seeing, Rebecca
over there being seen.
Can, by herself, can Rebecca
make contact with Rebecca?
No, cannot, because she's the same thing.
They got to be different to make contact.
GZHAN DANG GZHAN YANG PHRAD MI 'GYUR
Things that are, a thing which is itself
cannot make contact with itself,
and a thing which is different
can't make contact with
something else either.
That's the verse.
The first half is easy.
Rebecca can't contact herself,
but neither can she contact Geshe-la,
who is different. Why?
If they were different, they
couldn't really make contact
because there can't be a point of sharing,
because at that point of
sharing, they would be the same.
To be truly different
means no contact, ever.
If we share a point of contact
then we're not truly
different. We overlap somehow.
Okay?
It's not possible for me to touch her,
to make contact. It's not possible.
We think so, but that's a
seed opening in our mind.
But actually the two
physical things cannot touch,
not possible.
And you know in mathematics it's possible
because the point is theoretical.
It's just an idea, there's
no width to a point.
But in reality there would have to be
a point of contact that had width.
And then that would be a
certain kind of millimeters,
but if you took half of that millimeter,
could there still be contact? Like that.
And you go forever.
Okay, all right.
Next verse.
,PHRAD BZHIN PA DANG PHRAD PA DANG,
,PHRAD PA PO YANG YOD MA YIN,
PHRAD BZHIN PA means 'touching',
the BZHIN PA, right, Tim?, I-N-G.
Touching, and being in
the act of touching,
the touching and the toucher, don't exist.
That's Nagarjuna's next statement.
I like Choney Lama's explanations.
And I'm not going to
do Choney Lama with you
because it would take 20 years.
But in this case it's kind of sweet.
So let's go read Choney Lama.
PHRAD PA NGO BO NYID KYIS YOD NA
If things make contact
in and of themselves.
CHA THAMS CAD NAS PHRAD DAM,
PHYOGS GCIG PHRAD LA
If two things make contact,
does every part of the
two things make contact,
or does only part of the
two things make contact?
First, here we go, if Geshe-la
made contact with Rebecca,
would it be that every part of Geshe-la
makes contact with Rebecca?
Or just some parts of Geshe-la
make contact with Rebecca?
Which one?
The second one, because I can't...
if all the parts of me make contact
with all the parts of her,
I'd be inside her body,
we'd be exactly the same
height, and like that.
So, you know, it's
natural to say, "Geshe-la,
if you ever make contact with Rebecca,
like you do this elbow thing,
then it's only the tip of your elbow
and the tip of her elbow."
PHYOGS GCIG MA PHRAD PA GANG YIN (Busted)
DANG PO LTAR NA CHA THAMS
CAD NAS THAMS CAD DU
GCIG CING 'DRES PAR 'GYUR
If it's that every part of Geshe-la
makes contact with every part of Rebecca
then they would be mixed
together inseparably.
PHYI MA LTAR NA
Now if it's just part
of Geshe-la that touches
just part of Rebecca,
PHYI MA LTAR NA NGO BO NYID
KYIS PHRAD PA 'GAL BAS,
PHRAD BZHIN PA DANG PHRAD ZIN PA
DANG PHRAD PA PO RNAMS NGO BOS
GRUB PA YANG YOD PA MA YIN NO,,
NGO BO NYID KYIS PHRAD PA 'GAL BAS
If you're saying that it's
just one part of Geshe-la
that makes contact with Rebecca,
then the idea of contact is destroyed.
Why?
Because then there
would have to be a point
where we were the same.
Some part of Michael would
have to be part of Rebecca
if there was contact.
And then it wouldn't be two
different people making contact.
PHRAD BZHIN PA DANG PHRAD ZIN PA
He clarifies the root text by saying
PHRAD ZIN PA
for the second PHRAD
The first PHRAD is okay,
'touching', and then our author
adds E-D to the second, 'touched'.
And then, the toucher cannot
exist in and of themselves.
If they did they couldn't touch.
Now the part I like, why
I'm reading you Choney Lama,
is his last statement here,
which is very helpful.
Because we need help, right?
RANG LUGS NI, THA SNYAD DU
MA BU DANG ME SHING DANG
'O CHU SOGS LA PHRAD PA'I
CHA YOD PAR 'DOD KYANG,
Look, so Nagarjuna,
what's your RANG LUGS?
What's that mean?
Tim, what's RANG LUGS?
Yes, what's your position, Nagarjuna?
You know, you've been like just saying
a 1,000 times what's wrong.
Can you tell us what your position is?
Which he does not do.
It's not his habit.
But, so Choney Lama
puts words in his mouth.
He says, THA SNYAD DU
Nominally, in words only, yes,
a mother can touch her child,
fire can touch firewood,
and you can mix milk and water together.
By the way, the image of milk,
mixing milk and water together
is famous in Buddhism.
Do you remember why?
[student responding indistinctly]
Yes, dividing ultimate
reality from relative reality.
And they say there's a
tradition in ancient Asia
that ducks, if you mix
water and milk together
in a glass and offer it
to a goose or a duck,
they can drink the milk
and leave the water.
So they say that's easier
than picking emptiness out
of relative reality [Laughs].
So anyway, can you mix water and milk?
Can you, can a fire burn a piece of wood?
Can a mother touch her child?
We say is there a PHRAD PA'I CHA,
is there a point of contact?
And we say YOD 'DOD 'DOD
Now I'm Nagarjuna, 'DOD,
but only THA SNYAD DU,
only nominally, only in words.
What's it mean, only in words?
MING @DE SHAG MTSAMS
Words doesn't mean words here,
words means mental pictures.
In pictures, the pictures
can meet, that's okay.
The pictures can meet, but in reality,
outside, they never meet.
Now, here he nails it down, okay,
Choney Lama, yay Choney Lama.
PHRAD PA'I TSUL
You want to know how they make contact?
DON DAM DPYOD BYED KYI
RIGS PAS DPYAD PA'I TSE
If you really dig into it,
MI RNYED
You cannot find it.
If you just relax and
shake Rebecca's hands,
okay that's fine, you touched her.
Leave it at that.
What's that called?
@BDAG MIN
Don't dig, don't dig into it.
You want to shake her
hand, shake her hand.
Okay, shake hands. Make a contract, yay!
Now, but if you really dig into it,
you never shook hands,
therefore the contract
doesn't hold, right?
(student laughing)
Something like that (laughs).
So if you really dig into it,
@MA BDAG MA DPYAD PAR means
'if you just go through
your everyday life',
say your Medicine Buddha mantras,
you know, somebody gets
helped, that's okay.
Don't dig too deep.
But if you really look into it,
the mantra never touches the cancer.
So what's really going on?
That's if you ask beyond the pictures.
If you stay in the realm of
the pictures everything's okay.
Makes sense.
If you try to explain it
without mental pictures,
the mantra can't work.
Cool?
We finished the chapter, yay!
We finished the chapter on sansarga.
What's that mean, sansarga?
Not Sansara.
- [Student] Coming together.
- Yes, coming together and making contact.
You can make contact with other things,
but it's only happening
through mental images
and not really outside.
The picture I had for that last one,
by the way, was an intersection.
And is it possible that somehow
Geshe-la intersects with Rebecca?
Yes, if you don't look too close.
All right, see you guys
in the next chapter.